Thank you all for having me.
It's exciting to be here.
One of my favorite
things is talking about
what is going on
inside neural networks,
or at least what we're
trying to figure out
is going on inside
neural networks.
So it's always fun
to chat about that.
Oh, gosh, I have to figure
out how to kind of do things.
OK.
What?
There we go.
Now, we are advancing slides.
That seems promising.
So I think interpretability
means lots of different things
to different people.
It's a very broad term.
And people mean all sorts
of different things by it.
And so I wanted to talk
just briefly about the kind
of interpretability that
I spend my time thinking
about, which is what I'd call
mechanistic interpretability.
So most of my work actually
has not been on language models
or on RNNs or transformers,
but on understanding vision
ConvNets and trying
to understand
how do the parameters
in those models
actually map to algorithms.
So you can think of the
parameters of a neural network
as being like a compiled
computer program
and that the neurons are kind
of like variables or registers.
And somehow there are these
complex computer programs that
are embedded in those weights.
And we'd like to turn them
back in to computer programs
that humans can understand.
It's a kind of reverse
engineering problem.
And so this is kind
of a fun example
that we found where
there was a car neuron.
And you could actually see
that we have the car neuron.
And it's constructed
from a wheel neuron.
And it looks for--
in the case of the
wheel neuron, it's
looking for the
wheels on the bottom.
Those are positive weights.
And it doesn't want
to see them on top.
So it has negative
weights there.
And there's also
a window neuron.
It's looking for the windows on
the top and not on the bottom.
And so what we're
actually seeing there,
right, it's an algorithm.
It's an algorithm
that goes and turns.
It's saying, well, cars
has wheels on the bottom
and windows on the top
and chrome in the middle.
And that's actually just the
strongest neurons for that.
And so we're actually seeing
a meaningful algorithm.
And that's not an exception.
That's sort of the general
story that if you're
willing to go and look at
neural network weights,
and you're willing to
invest a lot of energy
in trying to
reverse-engineer them,
there's meaningful algorithms
written in the weights waiting
for you to find them.
And there's a bunch
of reasons I think
that's an interesting
thing to think about.
One is just no one knows
how to go and do the things
that neural networks can do.
Like, no one knows how to
write a computer program that
can accurately
classify ImageNet,
let alone the language modeling
tasks that we're doing.
No one knows how
to directly write
a computer program that can
do the things that GPT-3 does.
And yet somehow gradient descent
is able to go and discover
a way to do this.
And I want to know
what's going on.
I want to know what has
it discovered that it
can do in these systems?
There's another reason why
I think this is important,
which is safety.
So if we want to go and use
these systems in places where
they have a big
effect on the world,
I think a question
we need to ask
ourselves is, what happens
when these models have
unanticipated failure modes,
failure modes we didn't
know how to go and test for or
to look for or to check for?
How can we discover
those things, especially
if they're really
pathological failure modes,
that the model's, in some sense,
deliberately doing something
that we don't want?
Well, the only way that I
really see that we can do that
is if we can get to a
point where we really
understand what's going
on inside these systems.
And so that's another reason
that I'm interested in this.
Now, actually doing
interpretability
on language models and
transformers, it's new to me.
Before this year, I
spent, like, eight years
working on trying to reverse
engineer ConvNets, and vision
models.
And so the idea is in
this talk are new things
that I've been thinking
about with my collaborators.
And we're still probably
a month or two out,
maybe longer from
publishing them.
And this is also the
first public talk
that I've given on it.
So the things I'm going to talk
about, I think, honestly, it's
still a little bit
confused for me
and definitely are
going to be confused
in my articulation of them.
So if I say things
that are confusing,
please feel free to
ask me questions.
There might be
some points for me
to go quickly because
there's a lot of content.
But definitely at the end, I
will be available for a while
to chat about this stuff.
And, yeah, also I apologize
if I'm unfamiliar with Zoom
and make mistakes.
But, yeah, so with that
said, let's dive in.
And so I wanted to
start with a mystery.
Before we go and
try to actually dig
into what's going on
inside these models,
I want to motivate it by
a really strange piece
of behavior that we discovered
and wanted to understand.
And by the way, I
should say all this work
is done with my
colleagues in Anthropic,
and especially my colleagues
Catherine and Nelson.
OK, so on to the mystery.
I think probably the most
interesting and most exciting
thing about transformers
is their ability
to do in-context learning,
or sometimes people
will call it meta learning.
The GPT-3 paper goes
and describes things
as language models
are few-shot learners.
There's lots of impressive
things about GPT-3.
But they choose
to focus on that.
And now everyone's talking
about prompt engineering.
And Andrej Karpathy was joking
about how software 3.0 is
designing the prompt.
And so the ability
of language models
of these large transformers
to respond to their context
and learn from their context
and change their behavior
in response to their
context, it really
seems like probably
the most surprising
and striking and remarkable
thing about them.
And some of my
colleagues previously
published a paper that has a
trick in it that I really love,
which is so we're all used to
looking at learning curves.
You train your model.
And as your model trains,
the loss goes down.
Sometimes it's a little
bit discontinuous.
But it goes down.
Another thing that you can
do is you can go and take
a fully trained model.
And you can go and ask--
as we go through the context,
as we go and we predict
the first token and
then the second token
and the third
token, we get better
at predicting each token because
we have more information to go
and predict it on.
So the first token,
the loss should
be the entropy of the unigrams.
And then the next token should
be the entry of the bigrams.
Then it falls.
But it keeps falling.
And it keeps getting better.
And in some sense, that's
the model's ability
to go and predict, to go
and do in-context learning.
The ability to go
and predict, to be
better at predicting
later tokens
than you are at predicting early
tokens, that is, in some sense,
a mathematical
definition of what
it means to be good at this
magical in-context learning,
or meta learning, that
these models can do.
And so that's kind of cool
because that gives us a way
to go and look at what
our models are good,
at in-context learning.
Chris?
Yeah.
If I could just ask a
question, like a clarification
on what you mean by that.
Yeah, please.
When you say learning, there
are no actual parameter updates
happening here, is that right?
Oh, yeah, that is
the remarkable thing
about in-context
learning, right?
So, yeah, we traditionally
think about neural networks
as learning over the
course of training
by going and modifying
their parameters.
But somehow models
appear to also be
able to learn, in some sense.
If you give them a couple
examples in their context,
they can then go and do
that later in their context,
even though no
parameter's changed.
And so it's some kind of quite
different notion of learning,
as you're gesturing.
I think that's
making more sense.
So I mean, could you also just
describe in-context learning
in this case as conditioning,
as in, like, conditioning
on the first 5 tokens
of a 10-token sentence?
And predict the next 5 tokens?
Yeah.
I think the reason
that people sometimes
think about this as in-context
learning, or meta learning,
is that you can do things where
you actually take a training
set.
And you embed the training
set in your context,
like just two or three examples.
And then suddenly your model
can go and do this task.
And so you can do
a few-shot learning
by embedding things
in the context.
[INAUDIBLE]
So yeah, the formal
setup is that you're just
conditioning on this context.
And it's just that
somehow this ability--
like there's some sense for
a long time, people were--
I mean, I guess really
the history of this
is that we started to get good
at neural networks learning,
right?
And we could go and train
language-- or train vision
models and language
models that could
do all these remarkable things.
But then people
started to be like,
well, these systems, they
take so many more examples
than humans do to go and learn.
How can we go and fix this?
And we had all these ideas
about meta learning developed,
where we want it to go and
train models explicitly
to be able to learn
from a few examples.
And people developed all
these complicated schemes.
And the truly, absurd thing
about transformer language
models is without
any effort at all,
we get this for free,
that you can go and just
give them a couple of
examples in their context.
And they can learn
in their context
to go and do new things.
I think that was--
that was, in some sense,
the most striking thing
about the GPT-3 paper.
And so yeah, this
ability to go and have
the just conditioning
on a context
go and give you new abilities
for free and the ability
to generalize to new
things is, in some sense,
to me, the most striking
and shocking thing
about transformer
language models.
It makes sense.
I guess from my
perspective, I'm trying
to square the notion of learning
in this case with if you
or I were given a prompt of,
like, 1 plus 1 equals 2, 2
plus 3 equals 5 as the
sort of few-shot setup.
And then somebody else
put, like, 5 plus 3 equals,
and we had to fill it out.
In that case I wouldn't say
that we've learned arithmetic
because we already
sort of knew it.
But rather we're just sort
of conditioning on the prompt
to know what it is that we
should then generate, right?
But it seems to me like that's--
So that's--
Uh-huh?
Yeah, I think that's
on the spectrum,
though, because you
can also go and give
completely nonsensical problems,
where the model would never
have seen, like,
mimic this function
and give a couple of
examples of the function.
And the model's
never seen it before.
And it can go and do that
later in the context.
And I think what you did learn
in a lot of these cases--
so you might not have
learned arithmetic.
You might have had some
innate faculty for arithmetic
that you're using.
But you might have learned,
oh, OK, right now we're
doing arithmetic problems.
Got it.
And in the sense, I agree that
there's an element of semantics
here.
Yeah.
No, this is helpful
though just to clarify
exactly sort of what you
mean by in-context learning.
Thank you for
walking through this.
Of course.
So something that's I think
really striking about all of us
is-- well, OK, so
we've talked about how
we can sort of look
at the learning curve,
and we can also look at this
in-context learning curve.
But really, those
are just two slices
of a two-dimensional space.
So in some sense, the
more fundamental thing
is how good are we at predicting
the n-th token at any given
point in training?
And something that you'll
notice if you look at this--
so when we talk
about the loss curve,
where we're just talking if you
average over this dimension,
if you average like
this and project
on to the training step,
that's your loss curve.
And then the thing that we are
calling in-context learning
curve is just this line--
yeah, this line down
at the end here.
And something that's
kind of striking
is there's this
discontinuity in it.
There's this point
where the model seems
to get radically better in
a very, very short time span
and going and
predicting late tokens.
So it's not that different
in early time steps.
But in late time steps
suddenly, you get better.
And a way that you can
make this more striking
is you can take the
difference in your ability
to predict the 50th
token and your ability
to predict the 500th token.
You can subtract from the 500th
token the 50th token loss.
And what you see is that
over the course of training,
you're not very good at this.
And you get a little bit better.
And then suddenly,
you have this cliff.
And then you never get
better than-- the difference
between these, at least,
never gets better.
So the model gets better
at predicting things.
But its ability
to go and predict
late tokens over early
tokens never gets better.
And so there's-- in the span
of just a few hundred steps
in training, the model has
gotten radically better at its
ability to go and do this
kind of in-context learning.
And so you might ask, what's
going on at that point?
And this is just one model.
Well, so, first
of all, it's worth
noting this isn't
a small change.
We don't think about
this very often.
But often, we just
look at loss curves.
And we're like, did the model
do better than another model
or worse than another model?
But you can think of
this in terms of nats.
It's just the information
theoretic quantity.
And you can convert
that into to bits.
And so one way you can interpret
this is it's something roughly
like the model at 0.4
nats is about 0.5 bits
is about every other token the
model gets to go and sample
twice and pick the better one.
It's actually-- it's
even stronger than that.
That's a sort of
an underestimate
of how big a deal going and
getting better by 0.4 nats is.
So this is a real big difference
in the model's ability
to go and predict late tokens.
And we can visualize
this in different ways.
We can also go and ask,
how much better are we
getting at going and
predicting later tokens?
And look at the
derivative, and then we
can see very
clearly that there's
some kind of discontinuity in
that derivative at this point.
And we could take the
second derivative then.
And we can-- well, derivative
with respect to training.
And now we see that
there's very, very clearly
this line here.
So something in just the
span of a few hundred steps
is causing some big change.
And we have some kind of
phase change going on.
And this is true
across model sizes.
You can actually see it a
little bit in the loss curve.
And there's this
little bump here.
And that corresponds
to the point
where you have this change.
We actually could have seen
in the loss curve earlier too.
It's this bump here.
Excuse me.
So we have this phase
change going on.
And there's, I think, a really
tempting theory to have,
which is that somehow,
this change in the model's
output and its behaviors
and in these sort
of outward-facing properties
corresponds presumably
to some kind of change
in the algorithms that
are running inside the model.
So if we observe this big
phase change, especially
in a very small window
in the model's behavior,
presumably there's some
change in the circuits
inside the model
that is driving it.
At least, that's a
natural hypothesis.
So if we want to
ask that, though, we
need to go be able
to understand,
what are the algorithms that's
running inside the model?
How can we turn the
parameters in the model
back into those algorithms?
So that's going to be our goal.
Now, it's going to require
us to cover a lot of ground
in a relatively
short amount of time.
So I'm going to go
a little bit quickly
through the next section.
And I will highlight sort
of the key takeaways.
And then I will be very happy
to go and explore any of this
in as much depth--
I'm free for another
hour after this call
and just happy to
talk in as much depth
as people want about
the details of this.
So it turns out
this phase change
doesn't happen in a one-layer
attention-only transformer.
And it does happen in a
two-layer attention-only
transformer.
So if we could understand
a one-layer attention-only
transformer and a two-layer
attention-only transformer,
that might give us a pretty
big clue as to what's going on.
And so we're attention only.
We're also going to leave
out LayerNorm and biases
to simplify things.
So one way you could describe
an attention-only transformer
is we're going to
embed our tokens.
And then we're going to apply
a bunch of attention heads
and add them into
the residual strain
and then apply our unembedding.
And that will give
us our logits.
And we could go and write that
out as equations, if we want,
multiply it by an embedding
matrix, apply attention heads,
and then compute the
logits behind embedding.
And the part here
that's a little tricky
is understanding
the attention heads.
And this might be a
somewhat conventional way
of describing attention heads.
And it actually kind
of obscures a lot
of the structure
of attention heads.
I think that oftentimes it's
we make attention heads more
complex than they
are, or we sort of
hide the interesting structure.
So what is this saying?
Well, it's saying, for every
token, compute a value vector.
And then go and mix the
value vectors according
to the attention matrix.
And then project them
with the output matrix
back into the residual string.
So there's another
notation, which
you could think of this
as using tensor products
or using I guess left and
right multiplying this.
There's a few ways you
can interpret this.
But I'll just sort
of try to explain
what this notation means.
So this means for every
x, our residual stream,
we have a vector for
every single token.
And this means, go and multiply
independently the vector
for each token by WV.
So compute the value
vector for every token.
This one, on the
other hand, means--
notice that it's now on the--
A is on the left-hand side.
It means, go and multiply
the attention matrix--
or go and do linear
combinations of value vectors.
So don't change the
value vectors pointwise,
but go and mix them together
according to the attention
pattern.
Create our weighted sum.
And then, again, independently
for every position,
go and apply the output matrix.
And you can apply the
distributive property to this.
And it just reveals
that actually, it
didn't matter that
you did the attention
sort of in the middle.
You could have done the
attention at the beginning.
You could have
done it at the end.
That's independent.
And the thing that
actually matters
is there's this WV WO
matrix that describes--
what it's really saying is--
WV WO describes what information
the attention head reads
from each position and how it
writes it to its destination,
whereas A describes which tokens
we read from and write to.
And that's kind of getting
more the fundamental structure
in an attention head.
An attention head goes
and moves information
from one position to another.
And the process of which
position gets moved from
and to is independent from
what information gets moved.
And if you rewrite your
transformer that way--
well, first, we can
go and write the sum
of attention heads, just as--
in this form.
And then we can go in and
write that as the entire layer
by going and adding
in an identity.
And if we go and plug that
all in to our transformer
and go and expand, we have
to go and multiply everything
through.
We get this
interesting equation.
And so we get this one term.
This corresponds to
just the path directly
through the residual string.
And it's going to want to
store bigram statistics.
It's just-- all it gets
is the previous token
and tries to predict
the next token.
And so it gets to
try and predict--
try to store bigram statistics.
And then for every
attention head,
we get this matrix
that says, OK, well, we
have the attention pattern.
So it looks-- that
describes which
token looks at which token.
And we have this
matrix here, which
describes how, for
every possible token
you could attend to, how
it affects the logits.
And that's just a table
that you can look at.
It just says, for this attention
head, it looks at this token.
It's going to increase the
probability of these tokens.
In a one-layer
attention-only transformer,
that's all there is.
Yeah, so this is just
the interpretation
I was describing.
And another thing that's worth
noting is according to this,
the attention-only
transformer is linear
if you fix the
attention pattern.
Now, of course, the attention
pattern isn't fixed.
But whenever you
have the opportunity
to go and make something
linear, linear functions
are really easy to understand.
And so if you can fix a
small number of things
and make something
linear, that's
actually a lot of leverage.
OK.
And yeah, we could talk
about how the attention
pattern is computed as well.
If you expand it out, you'll
get an equation like this.
And notice-- well, I
think it'll be easier.
OK.
I think the core story,
though, to take away
from all of these is we
have these two matrices that
actually look kind of similar.
So this one here tells you,
if you attend to a token,
how are the logits affected?
And you can just think of
it as a giant matrix of,
for every possible
input token, how
is the logit-- how are the
logits affected by that token?
Are they made more
likely or less likely?
And we have this one,
which sort of says,
how much does every token want
to attend to every other token?
One way that you
can picture this
is, OK, there's really
three tokens involved
when we're thinking
about an attention head.
We have the token that we're
going to move information to
and that's attending backwards.
We have the source token that's
going to get attended to.
And we have the output
token whose logits
are going to be affected.
And you can just
trace through this.
So you can ask, what happens--
how does attending to this
token affect the output?
Well, first, we embed the token.
Then we multiply by WV
to get the value vector.
The information gets moved
by the attention pattern.
We multiply by WO to add it
back into the residual string.
We get hit by the end embedding.
And we affect the logits.
And that's where that
one matrix comes from.
And we can also
ask, what decides
whether a token gets a high
score when we're computing
the attention pattern?
And it just says,
embed the token.
Turn it into a query.
Embed the other token.
Turn it into a key.
And dot product them.
And so that's where those
two matrices come from.
So I know that I'm
going quite quickly.
Maybe I'll just
briefly pause here.
And if anyone wants to
ask for clarifications,
this would be a good time.
And then we'll actually go
and reverse engineer and say,
everything that's going on
in a one-layer attention-only
transformer is now in
the palm of our hands.
It's a very toy model.
No one actually uses one-layer
attention-only transformers.
But we'll be able to understand
the one-layer attention-only
transformer.
So just to be clear,
so you're saying
that the query-key circuit here
is learning retention rates?
And essentially, it
just ends up running
some of the attention
between different tokens?
Yeah, yeah.
So this matrix, when it--
yeah, all three of those parts
are learned.
But that's what expresses
whether a attention pattern--
yeah.
That's what generates
the attention patterns,
gets run for every
pair of tokens.
And you can think of
values in that matrix
as just being how
much every token wants
to attend to every other token
if it was in the context.
We're ignoring positional
embeddings here.
So there's a little bit that
we're sort of aligning over
there as well.
But sort of in a
global sense, how much
does every token want to
attend to every other token?
Right.
And the other circuit, like,
the output-value circuit,
is using the attention that's
calculated to, I guess,
affect the final outputs?
It's sort of saying,
if the attention head--
assume that the attention
head attends to some token.
So let's set aside the question
of how that gets computed.
Just assume that it
attends to some token.
How would it affect the outputs
if it attended to that token?
Mm-hmm.
And you can just calculate that.
It's just a big table of values
that says, for this token,
it's going to make
this token more likely.
This token will make
this token less likely.
Right.
OK, and that's just--
And it's completely independent.
Like, it's just two
separate matrices.
They're not-- the formulas
might make them seem entangled.
But they're actually separate.
Right.
To me, it seems like the--
like just supervision is coming
from the output value circuit.
And the query-key circuit
seems to be more unsupervised,
kind of thing,
because there's no--
I mean, there are--
just, I think,
in the sense that every--
yeah, in a model, every
neuron is, in some sense--
its signal is somehow downstream
from the ultimate signal.
And so, yeah, the
output-value signal--
the output-value
circuit is getting
more direct-- it's perhaps
getting more direct signal.
Correct.
But yeah.
Yes.
We will be able to dig into
this in lots of detail,
in as much detail as you
want, in a little bit.
So we can-- maybe
I'll push forward.
And I think also,
actually, an example
of how to use this to reverse
engineer a one-layer model
will maybe make it a
little bit more motivated.
OK.
So just to emphasize this,
there's three different tokens
that we can talk about.
There's the token
that gets attended to.
There's the token that
does the attention, which
I call the destination.
And then there's the
token that gets affected--
gets the next token, which its
probabilities are affected.
And so something we
can do is-- notice
that the only token that
connects to both of these
is the token that
gets attended to.
So these two are sort of--
they're bridged by
their interaction
with the source token.
So something that's
kind of natural
is to ask, for a
given source token,
how does it interact
with both of these?
So let's take, for instance,
the token "perfect."
Which tokens-- one
thing we can ask is,
which tokens want to
attend to "perfect"?
Well, apparently, the
tokens that most want
to attend to perfect are
"are," and "looks," and "is,"
and "provides."
So "are" is the most, "looks"
is the next most, and so on.
And then, when we
attend to "perfect"--
and this is with one
single attention head,
so it'd be different if we did
a different attention head--
it wants to really increase
the probability of "perfect,"
and then, to a lesser extent,
"super," and "absolute,"
and "pure."
And we can ask, what
sequences of tokens
are made more likely by
this particular set of--
this particular set of things
wanting to attend to each other
and becoming more likely?
Well, things of the form--
we have our token that
we attended back to.
And we have some skip of
some number of tokens.
They don't have to be adjacent.
But then, later on, we
see the token "are."
And it attends back to
"perfect" and increases
the probability of "perfect."
So you can think
of these as being--
like, we're sort of
creating-- changing
the probability of what we
might call skip trigrams, where
we have-- we skip over a
bunch of tokens in the middle.
But we're affecting the
probability, really,
of trigrams, so
"perfect," "are perfect,"
"perfect," "looks super."
We can look at another one.
So we get the token "large."
These tokens,
"contains," "using,"
"specify," want to go
and look back to it,
and an increase
in the probability
of "large" and "small."
And the skip trigrams
that are affected
are things like
"large," "using large,"
"large," "contains small,"
and things like this.
If we see the number two,
we increase the probability
of other numbers.
And we affect the
probability tokens,
or skip trigrams, like "two,"
"one two," "two," "has three."
Now, you're all in
a technical field.
So you'll probably
recognize this one.
We have "lambda."
And then we see backslash.
And then we want to
increase the probability
of "lambda," and "sorted,"
and "lambda," and "operator."
So it's all LaTeX.
It wants to-- if
it sees "lambda,"
it thinks that maybe next
time, I use a backslash.
I should go and put in
some LaTeX math symbol.
Also, same thing for HTML.
We see "nbsp" for a
non-breaking space.
Then we see an ampersand.
We want to go and
make that more likely.
The takeaway from
all this is that
a one-layer attention-only
transformer is totally
acting on these skip trigrams.
Everything that it does--
I mean, I guess it
also has this pathway
by which it affects bigrams.
But mostly, it's just
affecting these skip trigrams.
And there's lots of them.
It's just, like, these giant
tables of skip trigrams
that are made more
or less likely.
There's lots of other
fun things it does.
Sometimes the
tokenization will split up
a word in multiple ways.
So, like, we have "indy."
Well, that's not a good example.
We have the word "Pike."
And then we see the token P.
And then we predict "ike."
And we predict "spikes"
and stuff like that.
Or these ones are kind of fun.
Maybe they're actually worth
talking about for a second.
So we see the token "Lloyd."
And then we see an L, and
maybe we predict "Lloyd," or R,
and we predict "Ralph,"
C, "Catherine."
But we'll see in a second
that-- well, yeah, we'll
come back to that in a sec.
So we increase the probability
of things like "Lloyd," "Lloyd"
and "Lloyd," "Catherine."
Or "Pixmap"-- if anyone's
worked with QT, we see "Pixmap,"
and we increase the
probability of P,
"Pixmap" again, but
also Q, "Canvas."
But of course, there's
a problem with this,
which is, it doesn't get
to pick which one of these
goes with which one.
So if you want to go and
make "Pixmap," "Pixmap"
and "Pixmap," "QCanvas"
more profitable,
you also have to go
and make "Pixmap,"
"PCanvas" more probable.
And if you want to make
"Lloyd," "Lloyd" and "Lloyd,"
"Catherine" more
probable, you also
have to make "Lloyd," "Cloyd"
and "Lloyd," "Latherine"
more probable.
And so there's actually
bugs that transformers
have, like weird-- at
least in these really tiny,
one-layer attachment-only
transformers,
there's these bugs
that-- they seem
weird until you
realize that it's
this giant table of skip
trigrams that's operating.
And the nature of that is
that you're going to be--
it sort of forces
you, if you want
to go and do this,
to go and also make
some weird predictions.
Chris, quickly,
is there a reason
why the source tokens
here you have a space
before the first character?
Yes.
That's just the-- I
was giving examples
where the tokenization
breaks in a particular way.
And--
OK.
--because spaces get included
in the tokenization when
there's a space in
front of something,
and then there's an example
where the space isn't
in front of it, they can get
tokenized in different ways.
Got it.
Cool.
Thanks.
Yeah.
Great question.
OK, so just to abstract
away some common patterns
that we're seeing, I think one
pretty common thing is what you
might describe as like b, a, b.
So you go, and you
see some token,
and then you see another token
that might precede that token.
And then you're
like, ah, probably,
the token that I saw earlier
is going to occur again.
Or sometimes you predict a
slightly different token.
So maybe an example of the
first one is two, one, two.
But you can also
do two, has, three.
And so three isn't the same as
two, but it's kind of similar.
So that's one thing.
Another one is
this example, where
you have a token
that-- something
that's tokenized
together one time,
and then it's split apart.
So you see the token.
And then you see
something that might
be the first part of the token.
And then you predict
the second part.
I think the thing that's
really striking about this
is these are all, in some
ways, a really crude kind
of in-context learning.
And in particular, these
models get about 0.1 nats
rather than about 0.4 nats
of in-context learning.
And they never go
through the phase change.
So they're doing some kind
of really crude in-context
learning.
And also, they're dedicating
almost all their attention
heads to this kind of
crude in-context learning.
So they're not very good at
it, but they're dedicating
their capacity to it.
I'm noticing that it's 10:37.
I want to just check
how long I can go,
because maybe I should like
super-accelerate if this is--
Chris, I think it's fine,
because students are also
asking questions in between.
So you should be good.
OK, so maybe my plan
will be that I'll
talk until like 10:55 or 11:00.
Yeah, sure.
And then if you guys
want, I can go and answer
questions for a
while after that.
Yeah, it works.
Fantastic.
So you can see this
as a very crude kind
of in-context learning.
Like, basically,
what we're saying is,
it's sort of all the flavor
of, OK, well, I saw this token.
Probably, these other
tokens, the same token
or similar tokens are more
likely to go and occur later.
And look, this is
an opportunity that
sort of looks like
I could inject
the token that I saw earlier.
I'm going to inject it here
and say that it's more likely.
That's basically
what it's doing.
And it's dedicating almost
all of its capacity to that.
So it's sort of the
opposite of what we
thought with RNNs in the past.
Like, it used to be
that everyone was like,
oh, RNNs, it's so hard
to get them to care
about long-distance contexts.
You know, maybe we need to
go and use dams or something.
No.
If you train a
transformer, it dedicates--
and you give it a
long enough context,
it's dedicating almost
all of its capacity
to this type of stuff, which
is kind of interesting.
There are some
attention heads which
are more primarily positional.
Usually, we-- in
the model that I've
been training that
has two layer--
or it's only a one-layer
model-- has 12 attention heads.
And usually, around
two or three of those
will become these
more positional, sort
of shorter-term things
that do something more
like local trigram statistics.
And then everything else
becomes these skip trigrams.
Yeah, so some
takeaways from this.
You can understand one-layer
attention-only transformers
in terms of these
OV and QK circuits.
Transformers desperately want
to do in-context learning.
They desperately,
desperately, desperately want
to go and look at these
long-distance contexts
and go and predict things.
There's just so much
entropy that they
can go and reduce out of that.
The constraints of a one-layer
attention-only transformer
force it to make certain bugs if
it wants to do the right thing.
And if you freeze the
attention patterns,
these models are linear.
OK.
A quick aside, because
so far, this type of work
has required us to do a lot
of very manual inspection.
Like, we're looking through
these giant matrices.
But there's a way that
we can escape that.
We don't have to look
at these giant matrices
if we don't want to.
We can use eigenvalues
and eigenvectors.
So recall that an eigenvalue
and an eigenvector
just means that if you multiply
that vector by the matrix,
it's equivalent to just scaling.
And often, in my
experience, those
haven't been very useful
for interpretability,
because we're usually mapping
between different spaces.
But if you're mapping
onto the same space,
eigenvalues and eigenvectors
are a beautiful way
to think about things.
So we're going to draw
them on a radial plot.
And we're going to have a log
radial scale, because they're
going to vary-- their
magnitude is going to vary
by many orders of magnitude.
OK, so we can just go
in and our OV circuit
maps from tokens to tokens.
That's the same vector space
on the input and the output.
And we can ask, you
know, what does it
mean if we see eigenvalues
of a particular kind?
Well, positive
eigenvalues-- and this
is really the most important
part-- mean copying.
So if you have a
positive eigenvalue,
it means that there's
some set of tokens
where if you see them, you
increase their probability.
And if you have a lot
of positive eigenvalues,
you're doing a lot of copying.
If you only have positive
eigenvalues, everything you do
is copying.
Now, imaginary eigenvalues
mean that you see a token,
and then you want
to go and increase
the probability of
unrelated tokens.
And finally, negative
eigenvalues are anti-copying.
They're like, if
you see this token,
you make it less
probable in the future.
Well, that's really
nice, because now, we
don't have to go and dig through
these giant matrices that
are vocab size by vocab size.
We can just look
at the eigenvalues.
And so these are the
eigenvalues for our one-layer
attention-only transformer.
And we can see that
for many of these,
they're almost
entirely positive.
These one are sort
of entirely positive.
These ones are almost
entirely positive.
And really, these ones are
even almost entirely positive.
And there's only two that
have a significant number
of imaginary and
negative eigenvalues.
And so what this is telling us
is-- it's just in one picture.
We can see, OK, they're really--
10 out of 12 of these attention
heads are just doing copying.
They just are doing this
long-distance, well, I
saw a token, probably it's going
to occur again, type stuff.
That's kind of cool.
We can summarize
it really quickly.
OK.
Now, the other thing
that you can-- yeah,
so this is for a
second-- we're going
to look at a two-layer
model in a second.
And we'll see that
also, a lot of its heads
are doing this kind
of copying of stuff.
They have large
positive eigenvalues.
You can do a histogram.
Like, one thing
that's cool is you
can just add up the
eigenvalues and divide them
by their absolute values.
And you get a number
between 0 and 1,
which is like how copying--
how copying is just the head--
or between negative 1 and 1,
how copying is just the head.
And you can just do a histogram.
And you can see, oh yeah,
almost all of the heads
are doing lots of copying.
It's nice to be able to go
and summarize our model in a--
and I think this
is sort of like,
we've gone through a
very bottom-up way.
And we didn't start
with assumptions
about what the model is doing.
We tried to understand
its structure.
And then we were able to
summarize it in useful ways.
And now we're able to go
and say something about it.
Now, another thing
you might ask is,
what do you think the
eigenvalues of the QK circuit
mean?
And in our examples
so far, they haven't
been that-- they wouldn't
have been that interesting.
But in a minute, they will be.
And so I'll briefly
describe what they mean.
A positive eigenvalue
would mean you want
to attend to the same tokens.
An imaginary
eigenvalue-- and this
is what you would
mostly see in the models
that we've seen
so far-- means you
want to go in and attend to an
unrelated or a different token.
And a negative
eigenvalue would mean
you want to avoid attending
to the same token.
So that will be
relevant in a second.
Yeah, so those are
going to mostly
be useful to think about in
multilayer attention-only
transformers, when we can have
chains of attention heads.
And so we can ask,
you know-- well,
I'll get to that in a second.
Yeah, so that's a
table summarizing that.
Unfortunately, this approach
completely breaks down
once you have MLP layers.
MLP layers, now you have
these nonlinearities.
And so you don't
get this property
where your model
is mostly linear,
and you can just
look at a matrix.
But if you're working with only
attention-only transformers,
this is a very nice way
to think about things.
OK.
So recall that one-layer
attention-only transformers
don't undergo the space
change that we talked about
in the beginning.
Like, right now,
we're on a hunt.
We're trying to go and
answer this mystery of how
the-- what the hell is going
on in that phase change,
where models suddenly get
good at in-context learning.
We want to answer that.
And one-layer
attention-only transformers
don't undergo that phase change.
But two-layer attention-only
transformers do.
So we'd like to know what's
different about two-layer
attention-only transformers.
OK, well-- so in
our previous-- when
we were dealing with one-layer
attention-only transformers,
we were able to go and
rewrite them in this form.
And it gave us a lot of
structure-- of ability
to go and understand the model,
because we could go and say,
well, this is bigrams.
And then each one of these
is looking somewhere.
And we have this
matrix that describes
how it affects things.
And yeah, so that gave
us a lot of ability
to think about these things.
And we can also just write it
in this factored form, where
we have the embedding, and then
we have the attention heads,
and then we have
the unembedding.
OK.
Well-- oh, and for
simplicity, we often
go and write WOV for WO
WV, because they always
come together.
It's always the case.
Like, it's in some
sense an illusion
that WO and WV are
different matrices.
They're just one
low-rank matrix.
They're never-- they're
always used together.
And similarly, WQ and WK,
it's sort of an illusion
that they're different matrices.
There they're always
just used together.
And keys and queries are
just sort of-- they're
just an artifact of
these low-rank matrices.
So in any case, it's useful to
go and write those together.
OK, great.
So a two-layer attention-only
transformer, what we do
is we go through the
embedding matrix.
Then we go through the
layer 1 attention heads.
layer 2 attention heads.
And then we go through
the unembedding.
And for the attention
heads, we always
have this identity
as well, which
corresponds to just going
down the residual stream.
So we can go down
the residual stream,
or we can go through
an attention head.
On the next step, we can also
go down the residual stream,
or we can go through
an attention head.
And there's this useful
identity, the mixed product
identity, that any tensor
product or other ways
of interpreting
this obey, which is
that if you have an attention
head, and we have, say--
we have the weights, and
the attention pattern,
and the WOV matrix, and
the attention pattern.
The attention patterns
multiply together.
And the OV circuits
And they behave nicely.
OK, great.
So we can just expand
out that equation.
We can just take
that big product
we had at the beginning.
And we can just expand it out.
And we get three
different kinds of terms.
So one thing we do is
we get this path that
just goes directly through
the residual stream, where
we embed and unembed.
And that's going to want
to represent some bigram
statistics.
Then we get things that look
like the attention head terms
that we had previously.
And finally, we get
these terms that
correspond to going through
two attention heads.
Now, it's worth noting that
these terms are not actually
the same as their-- because
the attention head--
the attention patterns
in the second layer
can be computed from the
outputs of the first layer,
those are also going
to be more expressive.
But at a high level,
you can think of there
as being these three
different kinds of terms.
And we sometimes called these
terms virtual attention heads,
because they don't
exist in the sense--
like, they aren't sort
of explicitly represented
in the model.
But they, in fact--
they have an attention pattern.
They have no read circuit.
They're sort of, in almost
all functional ways,
like a tiny little
attention head.
And there's exponentially
many of them.
It turns out they're
not going to be
that important in this model.
But in other models,
they can be important.
Right.
So one thing that's
nice about this
is it allows us to think about
attention heads in a really
principled way.
We don't have to go
and think about--
I think there's-- like, people
look at attention patterns all
the time.
And I think a concern you
would have as well-- there's
multiple attention patterns.
Like, the information that's
being moved by one attention
head, it might have been move
there by another attention head
and not have originated there.
And it might still be
moved somewhere else.
But in fact, this gives us a way
to avoid all of those concerns
and just think about things
in a single principled way.
OK, in any case, an
important question to ask
is, how important how are
these different terms?
Like, we could
study all of them.
How important are they?
And it turns out, you can just--
there's an algorithm you can use
where you knock out attention--
knock out these
terms, and you go
and you ask, how
important are they?
And it turns out that by
far, the most important thing
is these individual
attention head
terms-- in this model, by
far the most important thing.
The virtual attention
heads basically
don't matter that much.
They only have an effect of 0.3
nats, using to the above ones.
And the bigrams are
still pretty useful.
So if we want to try to
understand this model,
we should probably go and
focus our attention on--
the virtual attention
heads are not
going to be the best way to
go and focus our attention,
especially since
there's a lot of them.
There's 124 of
them for 0.3 nats.
It's very little that you
would understand for studying
one of those terms.
So the thing that we
probably want to do--
we know that these
are bigram statistics.
So what we really
want to do is we
want to understand the
individual attention head
terms.
This is the algorithm.
I'm going to skip
over it for time.
We can ignore that term
because it's small.
And it turns out also
that the layer 2 attention
heads are doing way more
than layer 1 attention heads.
And that's not that surprising.
Like, the layer
2 attention heads
are more expressive
because they can
use the layer 1 attention heads
to construct their attention
patterns.
OK, so if we could
just go and understand
the layer 2
attention heads, we'd
probably understand a lot of
what's going on in this model.
And the trick is that the
attention heads are now
constructed from
the previous layer,
rather than just
from the tokens.
So this is still the
same, the attention head.
The attention pattern
is more complex.
And if you write it out, you
get this complex equation that
says, you embed the tokens.
Then you go and
you shuffle things
around using the attention
heads for the keys.
Then you multiply it by WQK.
Then you multiply
it, shuffle things
around again for the queries.
And then you go and
multiply by the embedding
again, because
they were embedded.
And then you get
back to the tokens.
But let's actually look at them.
So one thing that's-- remember
that when we see positive
eigenvalues in the OV
circuit, we're doing copying.
So one thing we can say
is, well, 7 out of 12,
and in fact, the ones with
the largest eigenvalues,
are doing copying.
So we still have a
lot of attention heads
that are doing copying.
And yeah, the QK circuit--
so one thing you
could do is you could
try to understand things in
terms of this more complex QK
equation.
You could also just try to
understand what the attention
patterns are doing empirically.
So let's look at one
of these copying ones.
I've given it the first
paragraph of Harry Potter.
And we can just look
at where it attends.
And something really
interesting happened.
So almost all the time,
we just attend back
to the first token we have, the
special token at the beginning
of the sequence.
And we usually think of that
as just being a null attention
operation.
It's a way for it
to not do anything.
In fact, if you look the value
vector, it's basically zero.
It's just not copying any
information from there.
But whenever we
see repeated text,
something interesting happens.
So when we get to
"Mr," it tries to look
at "and." it's a
little bit weak.
Then we get to "D," and
it attends to "urs."
That's interesting.
And then we get to "urs,"
and it tends to "ley."
And so it's not attending
to the same token.
It's attending to the same
token, shifted one forward.
Well, that's really interesting.
And there's actually a
lot of attention heads
that are doing this.
So here, we have one where
now, we hit the Potters,
"Pot," then we attended "ters."
Maybe that's the
same attention head.
I don't remember when I was
constructing this example.
It turns out this is
a super common thing.
So you go and you look
for the previous example.
You shift one forward.
And you're like, OK, well,
last time I saw this,
this is what happened.
Probably, the same thing
is going to happen.
And we can go and
look at the effect
that the attention
head has on the logits.
Most of the time, it's
not affecting things.
But in these cases, it's
able to go and predict--
when it's doing this, this
thing of going and looking one
forward, it's able to go
and predict the next token.
So we call this
an induction head.
An induction head looks
for the previous copy,
looks forward, and
says, ah, probably
the same thing that happened
last time is going to happen.
You can think of this as
being a nearest neighbors.
It's like an in-context
nearest neighbors algorithm.
It's going and searching
through your context,
finding similar things,
and then predicting
that's what's going
to happen next.
The way that these
actually work is--
I mean, there's
actually two ways.
But in a model that uses
rotary attention or something
like this, you only have one.
You shift your key--
first, you-- an
earlier attention head
shifts your key forward one.
So you would, like, take the
value of the previous token,
and you embed it in
your present token.
And then you have your query
and your key go and look at--
yeah, try to go and match.
So you look for the same thing.
And then you go and you
predict that whatever you saw
is going to be the next token.
So that's the
high-level algorithm.
Sometimes you can
do clever things
where, actually, it'll care
about multiple earlier tokens.
And it'll look for, like,
short phrases and so on.
So induction heads
can really vary
in how much of the previous
context they care about
or what aspects of the previous
context they care about.
But this general trick of
looking for the same thing,
shift forward, predict that,
is what induction heads do.
Lots of examples of this.
And the cool thing
is you can now--
you can use the QK eigenvalues
to characterize this.
You can say, well, we're looking
for the same thing, shifted
by one, but looking
for the same thing.
If you expand
through the attention
heads in the right
way, that'll work out.
And we're copying.
And so an induction
head is one which
has both positive OV
eigenvalues, and also
positive QK eigenvalues.
And so you can just
put that on a plot.
And you have your induction
heads in the corner.
So you have your OV eigenvalues,
your QK eigenvalues.
And I think, actually,
OV is this axis.
QK is this one.
Axis doesn't matter.
And in the corner, you
have your eigenvalues,
or your induction heads.
Yeah, and so this seems to be--
well, OK.
We now have an
actual hypothesis.
The hypothesis is, the way
that-- that phase change
we're seeing, the phase
change is the discovery
of these induction heads.
That would be the hypothesis.
And these are way more
effective than regular--
than this first
algorithm we had,
which was just sort
of blindly copy things
wherever it could be plausible.
Now we can go and actually
recognize patterns,
and look at what happened, and
predict that similar things are
going to happen again.
That's a way better algorithm.
Yeah, so there's other
attention heads that
are doing more local things.
I'm going to go and skip over
that and return to our mystery,
because I am
running out of time.
I have five more minutes.
OK, so what is going on with
this in-context learning?
Well, now we have a hypothesis.
Let's check it.
So we think it might
be induction heads.
And there's a few
reasons we believe this.
So one thing is going to
be that induction heads--
well, OK.
I'll just go over
to the evidence.
So one thing you can
do is you can just
oblate the attention heads.
And it turns out you
can color-- here,
we have attention heads
colored by how much they
are an induction head.
And this is the
start of the bump.
This is the end
of the bump here.
And we can see that they--
first of all, induction heads
are forming.
Like, previously, we didn't
have induction heads here.
Now, they're just
starting to form here.
And then we have really intense
induction heads here and here.
And the attention heads where
you oblate them, you get a--
you got a loss in-- so we're
looking not at the loss,
but at this meta-learning
score, the difference between--
or an in-context learning
score, the difference
between the 500th token
and the 50th token.
That's all explained
by induction heads.
Now, we actually have
one induction head
that doesn't contribute to it.
Actually, it does the opposite.
So that's kind of interesting.
Maybe it's doing something
shorter distance.
And there's also this
interesting thing where they
all rush to be induction heads.
And then they discover only
a few win out in the end.
So there's some interesting
dynamics going on there.
But it really seems like
in these small models,
all of in-context learning is
explained by these induction
heads.
OK, but what about large models?
Well, in large models,
it's going to be harder
to go and ask this.
But one thing you can
do is you can ask, OK,
we can look at our induction--
or our in-context learning
score over time.
We get this sharp phase change.
Oh, look.
Induction heads form at
exactly the same point in time.
So that's only
correlational evidence.
But it's pretty suggestive
correlational evidence,
especially given that we
have an obvious-- like,
the obvious the fact that
induction heads should
have is this.
I guess it could be that
there's other mechanisms being
discovered at the same
time in large models.
But it has to be in
a very small window.
So really suggests
that the thing
that's driving that change
is in-context learning.
OK, so obviously, induction
heads can go and copy text.
But a question you might ask
is, can they do translation?
Like, there's all
these amazing things
that models can do that it's
not obvious in-context learning,
or this sort of copying
mechanism, could do.
So I just want to very quickly
look at a few fun examples.
So here, we have an
attention pattern.
Oh, I guess I need
to open Lexoscope.
Hmm.
Let me try doing that again.
Sorry, I should have thought
this through a bit more
before this talk.
Chris, could you zoom
in a little, please?
Yeah, yeah.
Thank you.
OK, I'm not-- my French
isn't that great.
But my name is Christopher.
I'm from Canada.
What we can do
here is we can look
at where this
attention head attends
as we go and we do this.
And it'll become especially
clear on the second sentence.
So here, we're on the period.
And we tend to "je."
Now we're on-- and
"je" is I in French.
OK.
Now we're on the "I,"
and we attend to "suis."
And now we're on
the "am," and we
attend to "du," which is from,
and then "from" to "Canada."
And so we're doing a
cross-lingual induction
head, which we can
use for translation.
And indeed, if you
look at examples,
this is where it seems to--
this to be a major driving
force in the model's
ability to go
and correctly do translation.
Another fun example is--
I think maybe the
most impressive thing
about in-context learning to
me has been the model's ability
to go and learn
arbitrary functions.
Like, you just show
the model function.
It can start mimicking
that function.
Well, OK.
Chris, I have a question.
Yes?
So do these induction heads only
do kind of a look-ahead copy,
or can they also do some sort of
complex structure recognition?
Yeah, yeah.
So they can both use a larger
context, previous context,
and they can copy
more abstract things.
So like, the translation one is
showing you that they can copy,
rather than the literal
token, a translated version.
So it's what I call
soft induction head.
And yeah, you can have
them copy similar words.
You can have them look
at longer contexts.
It can look for more
structural things.
The way that we usually
characterize them is whether--
in large models-- is
whether they empirically
behave like an induction head.
So the definition gets
a little bit blurry
when you try to encompass
these more-- there's
sort of a blurry boundary.
But yeah, there seem to be
a lot of attention heads
that are doing sort of more
and more abstract versions.
OK.
Thank you.
Yeah.
My favorite version is this
one that I'm about to show you,
which is used--
let's isolate a single
one of these-- which
can do pattern recognition.
So it can learn functions in the
context and learn how to do it.
So I've just made up a
nonsense function here.
We're going to encode
one binary variable
with a choice of whether
to do a color or a month
as the first word.
Then we're going to-- so
we have green or June here.
Let's zoom in more.
So we have color or month
and animal or fruit.
And then we have to map it
to either true or false.
So that's our goal.
And it's going to be an XOR.
So we have a binary variable
represented in this way.
We do an XOR.
I'm pretty confident this was
never in the training set,
because I just made it up.
And it seems like
a nonsense problem.
OK, so then we can go
and ask, can the model
go and parse that?
Well, it can.
And it uses induction
heads to do it.
And what we can do is
we can look at the--
so we look at a
colon, where it's
going to go and try and
predict the next word.
And for instance, here,
we have April dog.
So it's a month
and then an animal.
And it should be true.
And what it does is it
looks for a previous--
previous cases where
there was an animal--
a month and then an
animal, especially one
where the month was the
same, and goes, and looks,
and says that it's true.
And so the model can go and
learn a function, a completely
arbitrary function,
by going and doing
this kind of pattern
recognition induction head.
And so this, to me, made
it a lot more plausible
that these models actually
can do in-context learning.
Like, the generality of
all these amazing things
we see these large
language models do
can be explained
by induction heads.
We don't know that.
It could be that there's
other things going on.
It's very possible that there's
lots of other things going on.
But it seems a lot
more plausible to me
than it did when we started.
I'm conscious that I
am actually over time.
Let me just quickly go
through these last few slides.
Yeah, so I think,
thinking about this
as like an in-context
nearest neighbors, I think,
is a really useful way
to think about this.
Other things could
absolutely be contributing.
This might explain
why transformers
do in-context learning over a
long context better than LSTMs.
An LSTM can't do
this, because it's not
linear in the amount
of compute it needs.
It's like quadratic or n log
n if it was really clever.
So transformers-- or LSTMs,
impossible to do this.
Transformers do do this.
And actually, they
diverge at the same point,
that if you looked--
well, I can go into this in
more detail after if you want.
There's a really nice paper
by Marcus Hutter explaining--
trying to predict
and explain why we
observe scaling laws in models.
It's worth noting that the
arguments in this paper
go exactly through
to this example--
this theory.
In fact, they sort
of work better
for the case of thinking
about this in-context learning
with, essentially, a nearest
neighbors algorithm, than they
do in the regular case.
So yeah.
I'm happy to answer questions.
I can go into as much detail as
people want about any of this.
And I can also, if
you send me an email,
send you more information
about all of this.
And yeah.
You know, again, this
work is not yet published.
And you don't have
to keep it secret.
But just, if you could be
thoughtful about the fact
that it's unpublished work
and probably is a month
or two away from coming out,
I'd be really grateful for that.
Thank you so much for your time.
Yeah.
Thanks a lot, Chris.
This was a great talk.
Thank you, Chris.
So I'll just open with
some general questions.
And then we can do a round of
questions from the students.
Sure.
So I was very excited to know,
so what is the line of work
that you're
currently working on?
Is it like extending this?
So what do you think is
the next things you'll
try to do to make it
more interpretable
over the next year?
I mean, I want to just reverse
engineer language models.
I want to figure out the
entirety of what's going on
in these language models.
And one thing that we
totally don't understand
is NLP layers, more--
we understand some
things about them.
But we don't really understand
NLP layers very well.
There's a lot of stuff
going on in large models
that we don't understand.
I want to know how
models do arithmetic.
I want to know--
another thing that I'm
very interested in is,
what's going on when you
have multiple speakers?
The model can
clearly represent--
like, it has like a basic theory
of mind, multiple speakers
in a dialogue.
I want to understand
what's going on with that.
But honestly, there's just
so much we don't understand.
It's really-- it's sort of
hard to answer the question,
because there's just
so much to figure out.
And we have a lot of
different threads of research
in doing this.
But yeah, the interpretability
team at Anthropic
is just sort of--
has a bunch of threads
trying to go and figure out
what's going inside
these models,
and sort of a similar flavor
to this of just trying
to figure out, how do
the parameters actually
encode algorithms?
And can we reverse
engineer those
into meaningful
computer programs
that we can understand?
Got it.
Another question I
had is like-- so you
were talking about how the
transformers are trying
to do meta-learning inherently.
So it's like-- and you
spent a lot of time talking
about the induction heads.
And that was like
very interesting.
But can you formalize the sort
of meta-learning algorithm
they might be learning?
Is it possible to say,
like, oh, maybe this
is a sort of like internal
algorithm that's going,
that's making them
good meta-learners,
or something like that?
Like, I don't know if--
Yeah.
I mean, I think--
so I think that there's
roughly two algorithms.
One is this algorithm we
saw in the one-layer model.
And we see it in other models
too, especially early on,
which is just, try to copy--
you saw a word.
Probably, a similar word
is going to happen later.
Look for places
that it might fit in
and increase the probability.
So that's one thing that we see.
And the other thing we
see is induction heads,
which you can just summarize
as in-context nearest
neighbors, basically.
And it seems-- possibly,
there's other things.
But it seems like
those two algorithms,
in the specific instantiations
that we are looking at,
seem to be what's driving
in-context learning.
That would be my present theory.
Yeah.
Sounds very interesting.
OK, so let's open a round
of student questions.
So yeah, feel free to go
ahead and ask questions.